<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from the lords at Oxford, and other lords whose names are subscribed, to the Lords of the Privy-Councell and the conservators of the peace of the kingdom of Scotland</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32942</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12790172</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12790172</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93931</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93931)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1034:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letter from the lords at Oxford, and other lords whose names are subscribed, to the Lords of the Privy-Councell and the conservators of the peace of the kingdom of Scotland</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>March 1, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained, cropped, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93931:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93931:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> LETTER FROM THE LORDS AT OXFORD and other LORDS whoſe names are SUBSCRIBED, TO THE LORDS OF <hi>THE PRIVY-COVNCELL</hi> and the Conſervators of the Peace of the Kingdom of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>OXFORD <hi>March</hi> 1. Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD Printer <hi>to the Vniverſity</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:93931:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93931:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Our very good Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F for no other Reaſon, yet that Poſterity may know Wee have done our duties, and not ſate ſtill while our brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> were tranſported with a dangerous and fatall miſunderſtanding, that the Reſolution now taken amongſt them for an expedition into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is agreeable to their obligation by the late Treaty, and to the Wiſhes and Deſires of this Kingdome, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the two Houſes of Parliament; We have thought it neceſſary to let your Lordſhips know, That if We had diſſented from that Act, it could never have been made a Law; And when you have examined and conſidered t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> names of us who ſubſcribe this Letter (who, Wee <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are too well known to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and to both Kingdoms, to be ſuſpected to want Affectione to R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligion, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Lawes and Liberties o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> or the Defence and maintenance of
<pb facs="tcp:93931:3"/> which we ſhall alwaies hold our Lives a cheap ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;) And when you are informed, That the Earles of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Thanet,</hi> and the Lords, <hi>Stafford, Stanhope, Coventry, Goring,</hi> and <hi>Craven,</hi> are in the parts beyond the Seas, and the Earle of <hi>Cheſterfield, Weſtmerland,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Mountague</hi> of <hi>Boughton,</hi> under reſtraint at <hi>London,</hi> for their Loyalty and Duty to His Majeſty and the Kingdome; your Lordſhips will eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, how very few now make up the Peeres at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> there being in Truth, not above five &amp; Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Lords preſent or privy to thoſe Counſells, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſent, conſenting or concurring with them: Whereas the Houſe of Peeres conſiſts of above one hundred, beſides Minors and Recuſant Lords, neither of which keep us company in this Addreſſe to your Lordſhips. How We and the Major part of the Houſe of Commons come to be abſent from thence, is ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious to all the World, that we believe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, cannot be ſtrangers to it; How ſeverall times du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſitting there, Multitudes of the meaneſt ſort of People, with weapons not agreeing with their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or cuſtome, in a manner very contrary and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Priviledge of Parliament, fill'd up the way between both Houſes, offering injuries both by words and Actions too, and laying violent hands upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Members, and crying out many hou<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the eſtabliſhed Lawes, in a moſt tumultuous and menacing way; How no remedy would be ſubmitted to for preventing thoſe Tumults; After <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlawfull, and Vnparliamentary <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tions, many
<pb facs="tcp:93931:3"/> many things rejected and ſetled upon ſolemne debate in the Houſe of Peeres, were again after many Threats, and Menaces reſumed, altered and determined contrary to the Cuſtome, and Lawes of Parliaments, and ſo, many of us withdrew our ſelves from thence, where We could not Sit, Speake and Vote, with Honour, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſafety, and are now kept from thence for our duty and Loyalty to our Soveraigne. And we muſt therefore proteſt againſt any Invitation, which hath been made to our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to enter this Kingdome with an Army, the ſame being as much againſt the deſires, as againſt the duty of the Lords and Commons of <hi>England.</hi> And wee doe conjure your Lordſhips by our common Allegiance, and Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on under one gratious Soveraigne, by the Amity and Affection between the two Nations, by the Treaty of Pacification, which by any ſuch Act is abſolutely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and by all Obligations both Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane which can preſerve Peace upon earth, to uſe your utmoſt endeavours to prevent the effuſion of ſo much Chriſtian blood, and the confuſion and Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which muſt follow the unjuſt Invaſion of this Kingdome, Which we, and, wee are confident, all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> men muſt interpret as a Deſigne of Conqueſt, and to impoſe new Lawes upon us. And therefore your Lordſhips may be aſſured wee ſhall not ſo farre forget our own intereſts, and the Honour of our Nation, as not to expoſe our Lives and Fortunes in the juſt and neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ence of the Kingdome: But if your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips in t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> have any doubts or apprehenſions, that
<pb facs="tcp:93931:4"/> there now is, or hereafter may be, a purpoſe to infringe your Lawes or Liberties from any Attempt of this Kingdom; We doe engage our Honours to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, to be our ſelves moſt religious obſervers of the Act of Pacification, and if the Breach and violation doe not firſt beginne within that Kingdome, We are moſt confident you ſhall never have cauſe to complain of this. And having thus farre expreſſed our ſelves to your Lordſhips, we hope to receive ſuch an Anſwer from you, as may be a means to preſerve a Right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding between the two Nations, and lay an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation upon us to continue,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>LORDSHIPS,</hi> most affectionate humble ſervants,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ed. Littleton C. S.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Cottington.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>D. <hi>Richmond.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>M. <hi>Hertford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>M. <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Huntington.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Bathon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Southampton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Dorſet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Northampton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Briſtoll.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Berkſhire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Cleveland.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Marlburgh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Rivers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Lindſey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Dover.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Peterburgh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Kingſton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Newport.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Portland.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>E. <hi>Carbery.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93931:4"/>
                     <item>V. <hi>Conway.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. <hi>Fauconbridge.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. <hi>Wilmot.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. <hi>Savile.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Mowbray</hi> &amp; <hi>Maltravers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Darcy</hi> &amp; <hi>Coniers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Wentworth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Rich,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Paget.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Digby.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Charleton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Deincourt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Lovelace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Poulet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Mohun.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Dunſmore.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Seymour.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Herbert.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Cobham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Capell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Percy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Leigh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Hatton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Hopton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Iermyn.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Loughborough.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Byron.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>L. <hi>Withrington.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
